<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>DART | The Data Assimilation Research Testbed</title><link>https://johnsonbk.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on DART | The Data Assimilation Research Testbed</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2021 15:08:08 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://johnsonbk.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>DART LAB</title><link>https://johnsonbk.github.io/tutorials/dart-lab/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 13:36:06 +0600</pubDate><guid>https://johnsonbk.github.io/tutorials/dart-lab/</guid><description>An introduction to Data Assimilation using MATLAB DART_LAB is a MATLAB®-based tutorial to demonstrate the principles of ensemble data assimilation. The DART_LAB tutorial begins at a more introductory level than the materials in the tutorial directory, and includes hands-on exercises.</description></item><item><title>The DART tutorial</title><link>https://johnsonbk.github.io/tutorials/dart-tutorial/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2019 13:32:54 +0600</pubDate><guid>https://johnsonbk.github.io/tutorials/dart-tutorial/</guid><description>The DART Tutorial is intended to aid in the understanding of ensemble data assimilation theory and consists of step-by-step concepts and companion exercises with DART.</description></item><item><title>WRF-DART tutorial</title><link>https://johnsonbk.github.io/tutorials/wrf-dart/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 13:36:06 +0600</pubDate><guid>https://johnsonbk.github.io/tutorials/wrf-dart/</guid><description>Overview The WRF-DART tutorial steps through a WRF-DART experiment. The experiment covers the continental United States and uses a 50 member ensemble initialized from NCEP’s Global Forecast System (GFS) initial conditions at 2017/04/27 00:00 UTC.</description></item><item><title>Model for Prediction across Scales</title><link>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/mpas/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2019 15:44:46 +0600</pubDate><guid>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/mpas/</guid><description>Data assimilation for MPAS is available as an ensemble Kalman filter (EnKF) implemented through Data Assimilation Research Testbed
This work is done in a collaborative effort between the Mesoscale and Microscale Meteorology (MMM) Division and the DART development team.</description></item><item><title>Open Geospace General Circulation Model</title><link>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/open_ggcm/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2019 15:55:44 +0600</pubDate><guid>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/open_ggcm/</guid><description>The primary goal of this project is to combine the OpenGGCM (Open Geospace General Circulation Model) with the NCAR Data Assimilation Research Testbed (DART), which implements an Ensemble Kalman Filter (EnKF) and will enable the sequential assimilation of ionosphere, thermosphere, and magnetosphere data.</description></item><item><title>Predicting Floods and Protecting Lives</title><link>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/wrf-hydro/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 14:58:06 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/wrf-hydro/</guid><description>Hurricanes are among the deadliest weather phenomena on earth. Hurricane damages are usually associated with strong winds and other related impacts, including storm surge, rainfall-induced floods and tornadoes.</description></item><item><title>Understanding Gulf of Mexico Eddy Dynamics</title><link>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/gulf-of-mexico/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2020 14:58:06 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/gulf-of-mexico/</guid><description>The Gulf Stream has been known to the Western world since the time of Juan Ponce de Leon&amp;rsquo;s expedition to Florida in 1513. It is an intense oceanic flow that runs northward along the U.</description></item><item><title>Next-Generation Space Weather Prediction</title><link>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/aether/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 14:58:06 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/aether/</guid><description>Space weather events can wreak widespread societal havoc, disabling satellites and causing outages of electrical grids on the ground. The potential for disruption is great enough that the National Science Foundation (NSF) and National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) committed to fund $17M to establish the next generation of space weather prediction systems.</description></item><item><title>GPS RO Observations and Tropical Cyclone Forecasting</title><link>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/gps/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2019 15:44:46 +0600</pubDate><guid>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/gps/</guid><description>Profiles of atmospheric quantities deduced from GPS Radio Occultation data are available in otherwise data-sparse regions and provide information used to forecast the behavior of tropical cyclones.</description></item><item><title>The Lorenz '96 model</title><link>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/lorenz_96/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2021 15:08:08 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/lorenz_96/</guid><description>The Lorenz &amp;lsquo;96 model is one of our favorite models. In our implementation, it is a 40-variable model that can be used to test inflation algorithms, the effects of localization schemes, the integrity of the DART installation itself, the state-space diagnostic routines; it is extensively used in the tutorial, and can even be run as a standalone executable to test the MPI support on a machine.</description></item><item><title>Planetary Boundary Layer</title><link>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/planetary-boundary-layer/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2021 15:03:37 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/planetary-boundary-layer/</guid><description>A long-term goal of this work is to find an efficient system for probabilistic planetary boundary layer (PBL) nowcasting that can be employed wherever surface observations are present.</description></item><item><title>Assimilation on Mars</title><link>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/mars/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2021 14:54:01 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/mars/</guid><description>The planetary atmospheres group at Caltech has produced a global and planetary version of NCAR&amp;rsquo;s Weather Research and Forecasting (WRF) Model. We are using DART to attempt data assimilation within the Mars atmosphere using the Mars version of WRF, MarsWRF, as our GCM.</description></item><item><title>Assimliation of CO</title><link>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/co_assim/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2021 14:48:20 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/co_assim/</guid><description>This project describes an integrated approach to modeling atmospheric chemistry with trace gas data assimilation. Specifically, we ran CMAQ from within DART to assimilate both synthetic and real observations of CO for the period of June 2001.</description></item><item><title>Chemical Data Assimilation</title><link>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/chemical/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2019 15:44:46 +0600</pubDate><guid>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/chemical/</guid><description>The program for Atmospheric Composition Remote Sensing &amp;amp; Prediction ACRESP in close collaboration with NCAR/DAReS, explored and built a capability for a chemical data assimilation system, as a tool for studies related to chemical weather and regional to global air quality.</description></item><item><title>Whole Atmosphere Community Climate Model</title><link>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/waccm/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2019 15:56:43 +0600</pubDate><guid>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/waccm/</guid><description>This is an excerpt from Applying the science and technology of data assimilation by Brian Bevirt 07/11/2017 as part of a CISL News series describing the many ways CISL improves modeling beyond providing supercomputing systems and facilities.</description></item><item><title>Forecast sensitivity analysis</title><link>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/sensitivity/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2019 15:44:46 +0600</pubDate><guid>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/sensitivity/</guid><description>Forecast sensitivity analysis provides an objective means of evaluating how initial condition errors affect a forecast and where to gather additional observations to reduce forecast errors.</description></item><item><title>Inertio Gravity Waves</title><link>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/inertio-gravity-waves/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2021 14:58:06 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://johnsonbk.github.io/research/inertio-gravity-waves/</guid><description>This project aims at quantifying the impact of various motion types in analysis and forecast fields by using normal modes. The DART/CAM is the main analysis system used in the project.</description></item></channel></rss>